Stanford
University okay um tonight we're going
to do a number of
things we're going to talk about
uncertainty we're going uh
to talk more about the shringer equation
the various versions of the Schrodinger
equation we're going to talk about how
things evolve with time we've talked
about that some
already uh let's see what else we have
here yeah we're going to apply the
shringer equation idea for the evolution
of systems to our favorite little system
of one spin but then if we have time and
I hope we will uh I would like to move
past the single spin we have we have a
general theory of quantum mechanics for
which I announced what the basic rules
were and the basic principles
her Mission operators are observables
vectors are states and so forth and so
on orthogonal vectors mean
distinguishable a very very
general set of
principles and so far we've applied it
to exactly one simple system the
simplest possible system in the world
we're not finished with it yet but
hopefully tonight or next time we will
move on to the next simple well no it's
the next next to next simpler system
there's a simpler one in between but uh
two spins two spins is the next to next
simplest system why do you think that
two spins are the next to next simplest
system as opposed to the next the
simplest a spin has two states how many
states do two spins have two um
orthogonal states to four so what
happened to the state with three states
the system with three states you can
imagine a system with only three states
that's the next to simplest so two spins
is the next next to simplest
but let's uh let's get on first of all
the concept of uncertainty I'm not going
to do the mathematical uncertainty
principle tonight but we should just
talk a little bit about the fact that uh
there are observables pairs of
observables which cannot simultaneously
be
measured uh
um the basic principle is that if you
measure something then by the definition
of a good measurement you leave the
system with the same value that you
measured otherwise you couldn't confirm
in the next round of uh you couldn't
confirm what you had measured so it's
important that you leave the system at
least momentarily or
instantaneously having the same value
that you measured
right uh the measurable quantities of a
system are the igen values of the
observable operators the obser The
Operators that represent observables and
the states in
which the observables are
definite in other words in which there's
no ambiguity about them the thing that
you get after you've done a measurement
of a certain quantity is an igen
vector or the igen vector s of the
observables now supposing we had two
observables which could be
simultaneously
measured if you measure you can measure
one and it will leave it in a state with
that same value but you can also measure
two things simultaneously it doesn't
matter it could be one after the other
but uh let's let's just call it
simultaneously you make two measurements
simultaneously of two different things
and you leave both of them
in igen vectors of the quantities that
were measured two
distinct
quantities that must mean that the
states that you leave things in are
simultaneous igen vectors of two of the
two distinct things if you can measure
things
simultaneously it means basically that
they have the same igen vectors or that
there
exist a complete set a basis a basis of
I incidentally the term somebody pointed
out to me that the
term
basis uh that I've been misusing it a
little bit and that's probably true I
use the term basis to mean a complete
set of
orthonormal vectors meaning to say
they're all orthogonal Quantum
physicists tend to use it that way uh I
think in
mathematics the notion of a basis does
not require the vectors to be orthogonal
it just requires them to be linearly
independent all right that's not a big
deal I just pointed out to you I will
use the term basis to mean a complete
set of orthogonal normalized
vectors um the igen vectors of an
observable can be made to be a complete
orthonormal basis when I say the can be
made to be I mean you you do have the
ambiguity what happens if there are two
igen values with exactly the same
value all right then you have an
ambiguity is what you how to choose the
igen vectors but you can choose them
perpendicular and if you have two
distinct operators which can be
simultaneously measured and therefore
simultaneously left in igen vectors of
those quantities it must mean that
there is a basis a basis of vectors
which are simultaneous igen vectors of
both quantities in other words there
exists a
basis if let's let's call the two
observables l and m these are Herm
Mission
operators l and
m and it means that if l and m are to be
simultaneously measurable it must mean
that there's a complete basis basis of
states which are both simultaneously
igen vectors of L and IG vectors of M so
that must mean that L on
I equals let's let's um let's use the
notation for igen values of L let's use
the notation little
L little L subi that's instead of Lambda
Elsa * I
that's the condition that I be an igen
Vector of L with igen value L sub I and
at the same time the same set of states
must be igen vectors of the M
observable and so this must be true for
a complete set of States
now let's apply l and m in sequence
first L then M and then try it the other
way way and see what we get so first
let's start with L on I here we have it
but now let's take
M multiply It by
L and then hit the igen vector I well
from the first relationship here this is
equal
to M * L sub I * I right all I've done
is plug in this first equation
but now Els subi that's just number
that's a number that's not even a matrix
it's just a good old number an igen
value and that means we can write it as
Elsa M *
I but we now know that M * I is just
Little
M so what does this give this gives L
sub i m sub I time I the
product okay that's not to surprising I
I is a thing which can be measured sorry
M and L are things which can both be
measured
simultaneously and if we multiply the
two of them together as matrices or as
operators they become another observable
whose igen values are just the products
good but if we did it exactly in the
opposite order l m on
I we would get exactly the same thing
the order these are just numbers and so
that the order that you write them down
doesn't matter L subi * m subi is the
same as M subi *
LBI and so this is equal to the same
thing same
thing now supposing you have two
operators which have exactly the same
action on every member of a
basis that means they will have the same
action on any superposition
of
vectors formed out of a superposition of
the basis vectors in other words they
will have the same action on any Vector
M * L and L * m have exactly the same
action on any vector and therefore M * L
is equal to l * m as operators all right
so we've proved the following
theorem that if two things are
simultaneously measurable
the two observables or the two operators
representing those observables commute L
time M and M * L are the same or L * m -
M * L which is the
commutator which is the
commutator L com commutator M must be
equal to
zero you can
prove a stronger form of this the theem
and it just goes the other way if you
have two operators I'll leave this to
you if you have two operators which
commute
remember if you have two operators which
commute it means that you can find a
complete basis of states in which both
of them
simultaneously in which the the complete
basis of states are simultaneous igen
vectors of the two operators it goes
both ways given that you have two things
which can simultaneously be
measured it follows that they commute
and if two things commute it follows
that they can be simultaneously measured
they have a complete set of common igen
vectors all right so the condition then
for things to be simultaneously
measurable is that they
commute what if they don't
commute in fact we already have some
examples of things that don't commute
Sigma X X and sigma Y and sigma Z no two
of them
commute no two of them commute with each
other and therefore they do not have
simultaneous igen vectors and that's no
surprise we know that the igen vectors
of Sigma Z are up and down the igen
vectors of Sigma X are left and right
and they're not the same thing they're
different they uh they don't Li they're
not they're not proportional to each
other so there are examples of operators
which don't commute in fact we're going
to work out the commutation relations
for them they don't commute in fact they
don't commute and that's an indication
that you can't measure them
simultaneously that's the idea of
uncertainty the the idea of uncertainty
is when you have two
objects two observables Each of which
you could decide to measure get a and
and get an answer you may not get you
may not know what the answer is going to
be it's statistical
but you can measure them after you've
measured them be certain you can repeat
the measurement and find consistency
each of them but not both of them okay
In classical physics there's no such
thing if you can measure a and you can
measure B then you can measure both A
and
B and you can be certain about both of
them if you can be certain about either
of
them all right so that's uh that's just
uh and we'll come back to that theme of
uncertainty and quantify it and quantify
it
um there may be
states where although you can't be
although you're not certain well all
right let's we'll come back to it we'll
come back to it we want a quantitative
measure of uh the necessary degree of
uncertainty in measuring two things
simultaneously and that is the
uncertainty principle but for the moment
we have the idea or an explanation of
why there are uncertainty uh uh between
observables in the first
place
yeah why have
twoes they have to
share
Comm well if you measure them and you
get answers for both of them you have to
leave the system in a state which is an
igen Vector of either one of them both
of them that's the rule when you measure
something it leaves it in a state of
definite thatness whatever that happens
to be which means an igen Vector if you
measure two things and you and and you
if you can measure two things
simultaneously it must mean the state
that you leave it in is an igen Vector
of both of
them
okay all right let's
uh let's come back
now
to the evolution of
systems as I said last
time I I went back and looked at the
classical mechanics uh
notes and I realized and I said okay I
have something like about 50 pages of
quantum notes the equivalent classically
was how many pages in The Classical
mechanics it was about half about a
quarter of a page I think just the
statement that states are sets of things
and uh that you can right on the
Blackboard points on the all right so 50
pages to get to where classical
mechanics we were
after about 30 seconds when we were and
that's just the way it is the next thing
we did when we talked about classical
mechanics we talked about how States
change with time that took another page
took another page arrows going from one
to the next and so forth here it's not
so bad it's not going to take us another
50 pages fortunately in fact we've
already laid it out it took basically uh
I I would say something like about five
pages or something in my notes I think
four or five page maybe a little more
maybe a little more so uh we're
beginning to compress and uh things are
once you got the idea of States then the
next is a little bit
easier okay so let's remind ourselves
what we said about the time Evolution
the Schrodinger equation the schinger
equation is the equation that govern the
time evolution of
systems we began with the idea of the
conservation of distinctions or
conservation of distinguishability of
states the implication was that states
which are orthogonal remain
orthogonal it was easy to prove from
that and you I hope you've proved it
it's e you should be able to prove
it uh that the U operator
I should have brought my own
pins the U operator remember what the U
operator is if you want to know what a
state is at a later time from its value
at time zero this stands for Time
Zero then you apply a certain
operation it's more than just an
operation it's a linear
operator okay a linear operator U and
you get S at time
T U of course is a function of T the
later or the earlier that you want to
project the vector forward you put in
different T's here and that was the
basic
equation but then we required another
ingredient and the other ingredient is
that orthogonal states stay
orthogonal so for example if we have two
orthogonal States let's call them for
the moment I and j instead of s i and
J are orthogonal in fact I and J might
be members of an orthonormal
basis let's take them to be members of
an orthonormal basis and then you allow
I to evolve for a time and you allow J
to evolve for a Time the bra the K
Vector I becomes U let's say U of T time
I if you start with i after a time it's
U of T of
i j
evolves with the hermiss conjugate of
u
j and the assumption is that if I and J
were authon
normal U * I and u startimes j are also
orthonormal so the way to say this is if
ji is equal to a chronica
Delta then this is also equal to a
chronica
delta in other words putting U and you
dagger sandwiching them between authon
normal bases here does not change the
inner product and from that you can
conclude since this is true for any
members of the basis that UD dagger
U is just the unit operator
we did this last time I know the unit
operator it does nothing UD dagger times
U then we went another step we said all
right let's consider the evolution from
Time Zero to an infinite tally short
time
later so we're interested in let's call
it U of
Epsilon where Epsilon is a small time
and we argued well first of all if
Epsilon is zero nothing happens to say
that nothing happens means that you is
the unit operator all right so U of zero
is just the unit operator it does
nothing just leaves the state the
same we added one more thing and that
was a kind of continuity I may not have
spelled it out a kind of continuity and
that was that youu of a small time is
close to the
identity in other words in a very small
period of time the state doesn't change
much so that's the same as saying that
uh U is equal to the unit operator plus
something
small of order
Epsilon and I used my freedom of
definitions just choosing definitions to
write this as minus I Epsilon *
H there was no content in that minus I
Epsilon I can just absorb it into h i
put it there in fact had I uh had I
really wanted to keep track of all the
interesting constants I would have put
an H bar over
here uh but this is all a matter of
convention whether or not we include an
H bar whether or not we include an i
whether or not we include an Epsilon is
simply a definition of how to of uh of H
we could have called this whole thing k
and then said K is equal to I Epsilon
over H you know what I mean I don't have
to say it more all right let's take away
the H H bar I'm going to forget it
anyway uh it's units simply
units and then we fed this oh let's
write the other one UD Dagger of Epsilon
is equal to 1 plus I Epsilon H dagger
dagger meaning Herm Mission conjugate
then we fed these two into the unitarity
condition and what did we find we found
that H minus H dagger must be equal to
zero that's what happens if you feed
these two into the unitarity condition
or another way to say it is H is equal
to H dagger or H is
hermiss now that's big news why is that
big news it means that H isn't
observable it's thing that we can
measure and uh we should be interested
in it what is it and of course the
answer is it's the H not of course but
as I said last time it is essentially it
is apart from a factor of plunks
constant it is the
hamiltonian what's it got to do with the
classical hamiltonian we talked about it
a little bit I'll come back to it but
for the moment it's just called the
quantum mechanical
hamiltonian it's a thing which in some
way or another well in a very clear way
generates Ates time
Evolution incidentally you might think
that this all right well let's let's go
on we we went a little bit another step
say okay let's write the equation s of
Epsilon this is pure review s of Epsilon
is equal to S of
zero minus I Epsilon
h s of Z
I just plugged in for What U
is and then transposed this to the left
hand side and divided by Epsilon
transposing to the left hand side makes
this minus and makes puts an equal sign
here and then divide by
Epsilon this is the obvious thing to do
and what do we get on the left
we get the time derivative of the state
Vector of the system the time derivative
of the state Vector of the
system
d
s by
DT is equal to minus i h s so what H is
is it's a rule for how you update the
state of a system if you know it at an
instant of time then at the next instant
of time it's you make an incremental
change in the state of the system
proportional to IUS i h * I it's a
little machine for telling you how to
update the state of the system now it
sounds awfully deterministic it sounds
awfully much like classical
determinism classical determinism is
also a set of rules for
updating uh the uh the state of a
system so in what sense are things not
deterministic
if you know how to change the state from
one instant of time to another well
they're not deterministic in the sense
that even if you know the state of a
system you simply don't know the results
of every
measurement the knowledge of the state
of a system in quantum mechanics is not
equivalent to the knowledge of the
outcome of every
experiment what does it tell you the
state of the system it tells you prob
abilities so this is basically a rule
for updating probabilities it's not a
rule for updating knowledge complete
knowledge of the state of the um of the
set of experiments that you could
do all right but in some sense or
another the state Vector evolves I I I
don't want to call it deterministically
because deterministically it carries
baggage with it but
it evolves in a known and definite way
now this is true but only if you don't
interfere with the system and classical
mechanics you can interfere with the
system arbitrarily gently and not uh
cause the cause any changes in the way
it's evolving in quantum mechanics when
you make a measurement you necessarily
disturb the system so this is the
evolution of the system of an UND of an
undisturbed system that is not in the
process of being measured yeah
what if the system happens to be in an i
state of the measurement you make all
right so what then then you would not
disturb the system ah well that's a
special case yeah you're right you're
right that's if you that's right if
you're in a special case of an igen
state of the system and you measure it
it doesn't disturb it uh so
right so that uh that is an exception to
what I said but generally speaking the
generic situation is when you measure
something you disturb something else
about the
system
okay this
equation is the shringer
equation
now it's sometimes called the
generalized shringer
equation the actual Schrodinger equation
of Schrodinger wrote it down was for a
particular kind of system the motion of
a particle
but it has exactly this
form this first became known as a
generalized Schrodinger equation and
then people dro the
generalized we now think of this as the
sh as a form of the Schrodinger equation
and what it is is it's an equation which
tells us how States change with time it
can be applied to the simplest system of
a single spin it can be applied to the
second simplest and the third simplest
system and to system of arbitrary
complexity but this is the form that it
has all right that's uh that's where we
more or or less were last time okay so
let's erase everything but the Stringer
equation actually this is called the
time dependent shringer equation the
time dependent Shing or equation is
equation for how things change with time
there's also another equation which is
called the time independent shinger
equation H is an
observable it corresponds to the
hamiltonian but hamiltonian is nothing
but energy at least in classical
mechanics so one might expect that H is
the operator that's representing the
observable energy of a system okay now
we're going to make a measurement of the
energy of some system how do we do it
let's not worry about that there's one
way we could do it we use eal mc^ 2
and then we weigh the system carefully
really really
carefully and in that way determine its
mass and its energy okay that's not a
very efficient way to do it because the
change of the energy of a system when
you heat it up or something is so
negligible that uh uh but that's one way
there are many ways to measure
energy but what are the possible
outcomes of the measurement of the
energy of a system
that of course depends on the system
it's not something you can ask answer in
general but uh depending on the system
for example if you measure the energies
of an
atom you get one
of a denumerable family of possible uh
answers namely the energy levels of the
atom if you measure the energies of a
harmonic oscillator again you get a
denumerable collection of possible
answers
if you measure the energy of a particle
moving in a non-closed
orbit
uh then in fact you get a continuous
possible family of possible answers so
the question of what the energies are
depends on the system and it depends on
the
choice of course it's not a choice you
the systems have hamiltonians it's not
up to you to to dictate to a system what
it's hamiltonian is uh it may be up to
you to try to discover what it's
hamiltonian is but let's use the
terminology you get to choose the
hamiltonian meaning to say you get to uh
to study different
possibilities and depending on the
choice of operator that you put here
that you call H you can get different
energy levels how do you describe how
sorry how do you calculate and determine
what the possible outcomes of the Energy
Measurement are you use the statement
that the values that the energy can take
on are the igen values of the
hamiltonian like any other observable so
you write another equation h
on let's call it the I now I now
represents an igen state of the
energy it doesn't represent any old
basis it represents in particular the uh
in fact maybe we should indicate that by
writing in
here the energy the I possible energy
level h on E subi is equal to the igen
value e subi times the igen vector
associated with that energy the notation
of putting eabi inside the K Vector just
means nothing more then this is the K
Vector which happens to be the igen
vector of H with igen value isi
and how many such esis are there well
there's a complete basis of them
whatever the dimensionality of the
system is whatever the dimensionality of
the space of states is there's that many
igen vectors of the
energy
and your job as a physicist is to try to
find
them
so that's the time independent shinger
equation
next thing we
did again a lot of review tonight next
thing we did was talk about the
evolution time evolution of expectation
values average values okay I complained
bitterly about terminology expectation
values all right but many many years ago
I gave up on this and so it's become
expectation value but it really should
be
average it's okay I'm okay with
expectation value I'll use expect but it
really should be
average
okay um and here's what we
found well what we said is the thing
that changes with time is the state
Vector so we're interested in
calculating s of t remember the
expectation value I'll just remind you
the expectation value you get by
sandwiching the
observable in a sandwich between the bra
version of the state vector and the K
version We proved this we proved that
this is the same as the average the
statistical
average uh and I won't go back over that
now this is the average value of L the
observable L and we can ask how it
changes with time it changes with time
because s changes with time and here we
know how s changes with time there's two
factors of s here so when we go to
differentiate this with respect to time
there will be two terms one coming from
differentiating this and one coming from
differentiating that
that if you remember that when you flip
from BR to K you have to complex
conjugate and that complex conjugating
changes the sign of I you will come to
the conclusion that this is equal to now
I always get the sign wrong let me try
to get the sign right I think it's minus
I
times
LH minus
HL average value of
that s
s we worked that
out we used that L on S gives you h on S
that's this piece over here and we used
that L when it acts to the left gives
you a term with h acting to the left
with a minus
sign okay so here's what we find then we
find that the time derivative of the
average of L
let's just write it this way d by
DT of the average of L I'll use that
notation for the average of
L as a function of time is equal to
minus
I times the average of the
commutator of L with the
hamiltonian if you know what the
hamiltonian is as an operator or as a
matrix and you know what L is as an
operator or a matrix you can
compute the expect the um the
commutator and when you've computed the
commutator you can compute its average
value just use this rule the sandwich
rule let's call it the sandwich
Rule and it tells you the left hand the
right hand side tells you what the
leftand side how it changes with time do
you find it odd that there's an i
there well I did the first time I saw
this first time I saw this I said wait a
minute wait a minute the time derivative
of a real thing can't be imaginary we're
going to find out that commutators of
real things are always imaginary so the
imaginary will go away we're going to do
some examples and you'll see this is
this is not hard to prove but we'll do
it by example
sometimes this is written in a short
hand the short hand is just a
dldt is equal to minus I * a commutator
of L with
h but at least at this stage of our
knowledge what this means is that it
should always be sandwiched and thought
of as a equation for the average values
of
things and so there we
have what I called the Heisenberg
equations of motion of a
system that brings us to the study of
commutators the study of
commutators and I want to go through
that just again a little
bit commutators have some rules
associated with them the the rules are
very very reminiscent of the rules for
proone
brackets so go back and read about
plusone
brackets I'll write down what the rules
are general rules algebraic rules of
plusone brackets and commutators and
then we'll just check are they really
true for both of them well the rules for
Pome brackets we did last quarter Pome
brackets are written this way
okay A B and I'm not going to write out
how you express them in terms of the p's
and q's of classical
mechanics but there was a few Simple
Rules associated with them first of all
there was some linearity
rules uh that if you uh that if you add
two operators oh sorry if you add two
things and then take the plus own
bracket with a third they add and so
forth this is certainly true of
commutators but there was a couple of
non-trivial rules
well first of all the Pome bracket is
odd which means that when you
interchange the two entries it changes
sign minus ba
a that was one property this is
certainly shared by the commutator if
you interchange l and H you interchange
these two terms and you change the sign
of the commutator so that's true of the
commutator
also
let's if a and b are now Quantum
variables this is also equal to minus B
*
a there's really only other one
important relationship and it's the
product rule the product of A and B
poned with
C the operation of
poning if you remember the Pome bracket
was a combination of derivatives
derivatives of various things uh if you
go and use that definition of the plus
bracket use the rule for derivatives of
products what you'll find out is that
this is equal to this Pome bracket side
uh it's equal to a time a Pome bracket
of B with
C plus the Pome bracket of B with c
times sorry Pome bracket of a with C
time
B now the order that you write down a
and the Pome bracket that's not
important these are just numbers I mean
these are just ordinary functions or
numbers and it doesn't matter which
order you multiply
them uh but I wrote them in an order
which I know that the commutator will
also
satisfy operators the order does matter
matter so I wrote These in a specific
order namely I put a on the left over
here and then I put B on the right over
here maybe it's not too surprising a
appears on the left in this uh factor
and B appears on the right so I kept the
order intact okay let's see if this is
true for commutators what would it say
it would
say well let's write it out a time
commutator BC
sorry go back it would
say that commutator of
ab with
C is equal to we'll put a question mark
here I don't know if it's equal to yet
a times a commutator of B with
C plus
a with
c yeah a with c times B let's check if
that's true this is very easy to do we
don't have to do any derivatives all we
have to do is write out the meaning of
this commutator of ab with C is the same
as AB * C minus C * a everybody see
why first you put AB on the left time C
and then you put C on the left and ab on
the right and you take the difference
definition of the
commutator let's see what we get on the
right hand side on the right hand side
we get a
times b c minus
CB that's this term and then from here
we get plus AC minus
CA time B these are operators now and in
this calcul their operators the order
matters okay let's see what we have we
have ABC here's ABC that's
good we have all right so this is this
is uh a friend we have minus
cab that's this one over here cab B
that's also a friend our enemies are a
CB but they occur both the same uh the
same way a b c no no a c b that's a bad
one but here we have also
ACB one with a minus sign one with a
plus sign so it's ACB minus
ACB and we're finished the commutator
satisfies the same algebraic rule as the
plus home
bracket is this an accident no of course
it's not an accident but we'll get to uh
we'll get to the deeper reason for it
eventually which comes first and which
which is more basic certainly the
commutator is more basic quantum
mechanics is more basic than classical
mechanics classical mechanics is an
approximation to Quantum Mechanics so it
stands to reason there ought to be a
classical approximation to the notion of
uh of commutator and there is
it's it's
uh that leads
us to speculate if you like but uh I'll
take it as not a speculation I'll take
it as something that we'll discover or
we'll be able to prove
later that when we go from quantum
mechanics to classical
mechanics the pone
bracket let's see um the pone bracket
becomes I think minus
I now this equality doesn't quite make
sense this is something classical on the
right hand side maybe we should put
arrows there
commutator a with
B uh in that last equation uh that you
wrote there it seems no no
the it seems like the right side is
twice what the left side is well I don't
think so a b c a b
c c a b c a b with a minus sign and then
we have a couple of extra terms the
extra terms are a minus
ACB plus
ACB yeah okay good you're allowed to
make
mistakes it's good slow me
down yeah yeah all right now nothing in
what I've done so far tells you that
this should be identified exactly with
that it might be identified with this
times a numerical multiple the bracket
might be seven times a commutator or a
quarter of the commutator and they would
all still make sense in fact there's a
dimensional difference between these
Pome brackets are derivatives of a with
respect to X derivative a b with respect
to P they have units which are different
than just a
b the difference of units is actually
soaked up in plun constant
if we work with plunk constant equal to
one then Pome brackets are just minus I
times
commutators but for dimensional reasons
there's an har bar there let's write it
another way let's put the H bar on the
left hand
side certainly
classically uh we think of commutators
is very small in fact we think of them
as essentially zero AB minus ba so in
the the classical limit the commutator
is something which is just zero how does
that happen well it's the H bar here
when har bar is very very small and
units in which H bar is very very small
which are just ordinary units I mean
units like meters seconds kilogram H bar
is an incredibly small number some 10 to
the minus or 30 I forget uh it's very
small number so in the classical
approximation commutators are negligi
negligibly small but when keeping track
of real quantum mechanics the commutator
is not
zero okay so that's that's
uh that's the meaning or the notion of
commutator and the nice property now is
that this relationship
here is simply the quantum analog of an
equation that we studied last quarter DL
by
DT is equal to the Pome bracket of L
with the
hamiltonian which matches quite well
with this that is the essential reason
at this stage for
identifying H with the
hamiltonian classical mechanics when
packaged in this fishy way called Pon
formulation the fishy formulation encaps
you know takes organizes everything into
relations involving Pome brackets and in
particular it says that d l by DT L
could be anything incidentally L here is
not the angular momentum it's anything d
l by DT is equal to the Pome bracket of
L with h and in quantum mechanics in the
in the in the sense of average value we
found that d l by DT is minus I times
the
commutator so that's that's the essence
of the connection between the
hamiltonian of classical mechanics and
class and quantum
mechanics
yeah of
what L is any
observable any observable I used L for
linear operator but of course it should
be Herm Mission linear operator so I
might have used H but then I would have
gotten caught and found that H H oh H is
for Mission and so is L but I used L for
a
generic uh
observable so assume that L is her
Mission originally I I used it for
linear
but now I'm using it to mean linear and
Herm mission
all right L could be h l could be
H right that's a that's uh we could
study the equation of motion of how H
changes with time or bet yet how the the
average of H changes with time let's do
so here we
are d h the the H by
DT is equal to minus I time the
commutator of H with h
but the commutator of anything with
itself is
zero and so incidentally is the Pome
bracket of anything with
itself because Pome brackets are odd
they change sign when you interchange
the two
objects that means the Pome bracket of a
thing with itself is zero so from a
classical point of view we could have
derived the conservation of energy from
the principle that the time derivative
of the energy is the POS
bracket of the energy with
itself here we find in quantum mechanics
a very simple thing similar thing the
time derivative of the again the
hamiltonian is the Pome bra uh is the
commutator of the hamiltonian with
itself and is therefore
zero energy is conserved in quantum
mechanics or at least the average of the
energy is conserved now it's it's better
than that there's a very definite sense
in which the energy is exactly
conserved but not for
tonight
the two what
if we had two spins yeah
absolutely absolutely in fact whenever
we build a system out of two
systems the in general the observables
for one of the systems and the
observable for the other systems commute
with each
other that's why you can measure the
position of me and Sanjay
simultaneously because we're
two because our position commute I uh
and so do our spins but uh I think
that's the
question that is the question you were
asking yeah okay
right yeah but we haven't come yet I was
that's where I was going to go later but
I don't know if we'll get to it um to
the question of composing systems taking
systems and making bigger systems out of
uh composing them and that would bring
us to the issue of
entanglement I I have a feeling we
probably won't quite get there but maybe
we'll at least partly get
there all right the next thing we want
to do is solve Schrodinger's equation I
don't mean the one for the igen values
and the igen vectors that we solve by
standard methods of if we if we happen
to know what the hamiltonian is and in
particular if we happen to know it in
some Matrix form then we're just
calculating the igen vectors and igen
values of some Matrix let's suppose
that's done we have the igen vectors we
have the igen Val
vales let's now find the general
solution of Schrodinger's equation in
other words how things evolve with
time you know I realiz that all of this
is abstract that uh the only system that
we have to apply this all to is the
world's simplest system again and that's
not very much so at this stage you're
probably saying to yourself when are we
going to be thinking about real things
objects uh
systems um we will We Will by all
means but I think having all of this
apparatus this abstract formulation of
quantum mechanics will make it very easy
and quick to uh to start applying it to
lots of things yeah yeah we know what H
is for
this for this spin system yet well okay
so all right let me let me answer that
right
now
um that depends on what we do with a
spin if we have a spin in free
space far from anything
else then its energy or its hamiltonian
is just basically zero incidentally
adding a constant to a hamiltonian
doesn't do anything and the reason is
because a constant commutes with
everything so apart from a possible
additive constant in the energy a spin
which is not around anything else it
just doesn't it's hamiltonian zero and
that means that it doesn't change with
time if you put it in a magnetic field
if it happens to be a real spin of an
electron you put it in a magnetic field
the magnetic field induces a hamiltonian
which I hope we'll get to tonight and it
causes the spin to do things to to have
a Time dependence
and then what the hamiltonian would be
would have to do with which direction
the magnetic field was
in so hamiltonians can be changed I mean
you can change a hamiltonian by changing
the direction of a of a magnetic
field but we'll we'll come we're I hope
we get to this example tonight but let's
just first write down the general
solution of uh of the shinger equation
to do
that we start by by saying let there be
a basis of igen vectors I guess we call
it this is the same as e
subi if I don't want to write eabi I
will just write the I igen Vector but it
means the igen vector with energy
eabi all right we can take any state
since I or eabi are a basis of States we
can take any
state let's call it
a or should we call it Sai let's see
what did I call it in my
notes no I think I called it Sai I did I
called it
Sai
s and let's think about s at Time
Zero well no let's leave the time
arbitrary
p is a sum of all of the igen states or
all the igen values of some set of
coefficients Alpha sub I I've used the
term Alpha in the past to denote the
coefficients of states of basis
vectors so any state whatever can be
written as a superposition of igen
vectors of the energy since the igen
vectors of a Herm Mission operator are a
complete basis right so this is and
let's say at time T equals
z now how does the how does the not a
time at time T how does the state change
with time what's changing here well the
states I are just a fixed set of States
it's the alphas which change the
coefficients here which change with
time all right so the coefficients in
the
expansion of an arbitrary state are
typically time depend in coefficients
that's what gives rise to a Time
dependence in expectation values and
other things now let's write the
Schrodinger equation so we have I side
dot sorry we have side dot which we can
now write let's take side dot d by DT of
s d side
DT that's equal from here summon
I the alpha sub I of t with respect to T
time I to differentiate the state all we
do is differentiate the individual
coefficients now Schrodinger's equation
tells us to set that equal to minus
I oh different ey holy
smoke
okay J J
okay set that equal to minus
I times H acting on this but H can be
brought in through the summation here
and this can just be written as
summation of I the coefficient numbers
Alpha summation of a j
j Alpha J of
t h
on
J now what is h on
J somebody said
zero no no
no
there I and E subi are the same vectors
go up to the top Vector to the top
equation h on the ien vector is the
energy e subi on the I Vector okay
so this just becomes e
subj here we have on the left hand side
a a
sum of basis vectors with coefficients
Alpha J sorry where are we did I make a
mistake
here oh oh sorry this should have gone
this should have gone down
here this is
wrong
here this should have gone down here
this is Su on
J D by DT of alpha
J and
then
h I'm
lost this is correct up to here this is
correct up to here let's uh
let's
okay yeah right let's let's go back to
here and now let's calculate the
uh
ah let's calculate the time derivative
of
this what do we do we put in minus
I times h on
J here is where I use h on J is equal to
EJ on J okay I think that's what I had a
moment ago anyway isn't it I think it's
exactly what I had minus I take out the
minus
I all right this thing and this thing
are the
same so this sum must be exactly the
same as this
sum if you have two sums of basis
vectors the coefficients must be the
same if you have two sets of bases
Vector uh sorry sorry if you have two
linear superpositions of the same set of
basis
vectors and they're equal to each other
then the individual coefficients have to
be equal to each other so it follows
that d alpha by
DT is equal to minus
itimes the alpha J by DT
EJ Alpha
J all I've done is set d alpha DT equal
to the coefficient in this equation over
here and that's the whole upshot it
tells you how the alphas change with
time for each J this is a differential
equation just think of this as just a
differential equation for Alpha what's
the solution of this differential
equation we've done this kind of
equation over and over again the time
derivative of something is proportional
to to the same thing to the thing
itself exponential solution right so the
solution of this equation is Alpha
J equals Alpha J at time Z * e to the
minus I EJ
T if we differentiate Alpha J with
respect to T it will bring down this
Factor minus i e subj times the same
thing
so we can now write the general solution
of the Schrodinger equation we've solved
it for each individual igen Vector this
is the way individual igen the
individual coefficients Alpha change
with time but now we can go
back let's go
back to the original
equation that the state vector
is a sum
over the igen vectors and let's plug in
what we now know about
Alpha we now have solved for Alpha and
here we can write that the General State
Vector at time
T if you know it at Time Zero let's
suppose we know it at Time
Zero at Time
Zero it was just Alpha J of
time0 time J
all that happens is each Alpha J picks
up a time dependence and the time
dependence is just governed by the
energy of the
state
earthquake all right so all you do to
find the general solution is you take
the state you break it up into igen
vectors of the
hamiltonian and then whatever it was at
Time Zero the only thing that happens is
the phase of each entry here changes
with time with an e to the minus itimes
the energy of the
state where would the H bar go in this
formula anybody
know
H underneath the eye or underneath
underneath the energy or underneath the
time it doesn't matter but it goes into
the into the denominator
here this is the connection between
energy and
oscillations okay this is the
oscillations of the wave function not
oscillations of real things but
oscillations of the um of the
coefficients of the state vectors
while we're at it let's do one more
thing let's use our general solution of
the Schrodinger
equation to
calculate how the average of L changes
with time we have an equation for it but
now we actually know how side changes
with time and this is just a little bit
of gy not gymnastics just a little bit
of uh fiddling around with equations
some some of you may recognize the
equation we're about to get but uh
whether you recognize it or not it's
just explaining how the symbols are used
if you like okay let's
calculate given that the
state changes like
so let's ask how the expectation
value of an arbitrary
observable changes what do you have to
know to know how the average or the
expectation value of L changes L is some
operator I haven't told you what
operator of course you need to know what
operator in order toh to say how it
changes of course you do but still we
can
uh we can go a little ways let's plug in
this formula for S of T this is sum of J
Alpha
subj e to the minus I
EJ
T time
J now we have
L put l over here and now we're going to
do the same thing to this bra Vector
over here but what happens when we do a
bra Vector let's do the bra Vector the
bra Vector is s of
T is summation we better use a different
summation variable
K and then we will have Alpha
star sub K
of0 when you go from bras to ks you have
to complex conjugate we'll also have to
change this to e to the plus I E sub K
T times the bra vector
k I've changed the summation index here
so that I don't don't confuse confuse it
with this one I've complex
conjugated complex conjugated here and
flipped from catch the bras all right so
I can put this over here summation over
a
k
k Alpha
star k Alpha star
k at time
zero this is a Time
Zero times e to the plus I E
KT so it's a double sum it's a double
sum over K and J that's not terribly
Illuminating but let's uh just uh just
uh for uh for fun let's work it out now
what's the inner product of K with J we
see here the inner oh no not not sorry
it's not the inner product of K with J
what we see here is L sandwiched between
J and K L sandwiched between J and K the
operator L acts on the state J and then
you project it onto K let's give that a
name let's call that L
KJ that's exactly the kind of Matrix
elements we computed when we talked
about the Matrix represent presentation
of
observables
the inner product of alpha sorry of L on
J with K that's what we called L KJ just
the Matrix
representation of the observable and
then we
have Alpha
star k of zero Alpha J of
zero we'll say we'll talk about that in
a moment and then we have a phase e to
the
i e sub K minus E
subj time
T summed over J and
K now the main reason I did this was
just to illustrate the Machinery I did
not do this because this is a formula of
uh of any importance right now but some
of you may nevertheless repres recognize
it it is Heisenberg's Matrix uh
formulation of quantum mechanics
Heisenberg's formulation of the
way averages change with time if you go
back to Heisenberg's first paper on
quantum mechanics he guessed this
formula basically just guess this
formula every observable has two
frequencies associated with it that was
weird it was common for people to
understand
that an observable might be an
oscillating observable it might be
something that oscillates and would have
a frequency associated with it but
Heisenberg said there are two
frequencies associated with every Matrix
element of an
observable this is where it came from no
this it came out of Heisenberg's head
but this is the way dur explained what
this is the way
durak um
understood what Heisenberg was saying
through this
Machinery first just a pieces the pieces
this represents the observable whatever
the observable is it's its Matrix
representation these things have to do
with the initial State the state at time
T equals
z and these things here have to do with
the way things change with time
everything changes with time with two
separate uh frequencies and then you sum
it all together and that tells you how L
changes with time how the average of L
changes with
time so we're putting together a bunch
of Machinery that we'll
use are there any
questions
yeah am I reading this correctly is it
the case that the magnitude of the stays
the same the alphas are fixed the alpas
are just the alpha at time t equal Z
period yeah yes you I think you're going
back to here yeah yes that's correct the
magnitudes of the alphas stay
fixed it's the relative phases between
them so all of the time Evolution has to
do with these relative phases yeah
soti is
what oh oh that it actually doesn't
matter this just means the whole
derivative with respect to time it's
usually written as a partial derivative
but it just
means it could be written as a total
derivative same thing s only depends on
time I mean also function same position
it's well yeah that's okay that's
right we will eventually come to think
of s as a function of time and position
and that's why it uh
uh but uh that's later for the moment it
doesn't matter whether we use partial
derivative or total derivative it just
means the change in s in a small
time uh and uh it doesn't matter whether
which yeah um when you derive the time
dependent trangular equation you use the
fact that the the states stay orthogonal
over time I think that's an empirical
fact
well it is an empirical
fact but in fact I think it's much more
than
that um the evidence that it's much more
than that is also an empirical fact it's
a curious empir empirical fact people
have tried to change quantum
mechanics and it seems to be as hard to
change quantum mechanics as it is to
change arithmetic or
logic
um if you start fooling around with it
and try to change the rules you very
quickly find that something really bad
happens probability is not
conserved um probability is not not
positive terrible nonlocalities happen
where you can communicate that the
infinite
distances
uh and so quantum mechanics is not a
thing which is easily changed in fact
there was no known changes that can be
made in it uh of course there is one
known change that can be made you can
just replace it by classical mechanics
that's a consistent Theory the reason
it's a consistent theory is because it's
a good limit of quantum
mechanics but there's no ways to change
it and a you know to deform it a little
bit my friend David finlin who was a
very wise is a very wise man a great
scientist once uh explained to me that
there are two kinds of Revolutions in
physics he called one a plastic flow and
the other a brittle
cracking what he meant by that um he
considered for example general
relativity to be a plastic flow you can
change it little bits you can deform it
a little bit you can change Einstein's
equations uh by uh by changing
variables it's it's not something that
you you cannot change at all and you can
change it in little ways and deform it
special relativity is very hard to
change once you change special
relativity uh it uh it's very
brittle and um the whole structure of it
goes down the drain but you probably but
nevertheless you could change it a
little bit it's harder to change in
general
relativity most things go wrong but
quantum mechanics is absolutely brittle
and by that he meant not that the theory
is in danger of being broken by
anything but that if you try to change
it you will get
broken
uh so quantum mechanics is very hard to
change and I think the evidence for that
is just all of the years over which
people have tried to change
it yeah so the
E those are both real
numbers is the reason that we know that
they're real numbers because the I
states that we chose are I states of the
yeah yes we derive from the
unit we derived from unitarity unitarity
is this condition that UD dagger U is
equal to one or I called unitarity from
that we derive that the hamiltonian is
her Mission and from that we can Define
we can derive that its igen values are
real
yeah M of of of what syntax syntax top
you have
H Vector equals of that first P of I on
the right hand side of the equation is a
is an I value no well okay
it's this whole thing is an igen value
igen
Vector but it's the IG Vector with igen
value e subi so you can you're labeling
the igen vectors by their igen
values
right here it's just the igen value
that's what
right and incidentally this is a case
where repeated indices do not get summed
over this is a case of the nons
summation
convention Let's uh apply some of this
apparatus to the problem of a single
spin a spin in a magnetic field
let's see if we can calculate in
particular how the average of the
components of the spins
change as we do
this depending on your memory for
classical physics you may start to find
some of it um
familiar if
not I will remind you
it's not as bad as fingers on the old
life no no it's not no no it is not no
that wasn't terribly bad it just reminds
me of my cat in the middle of the
night okay we have a single spin
let's put the spin into a magnetic
field if we put the spin into a magnetic
field along let's take the z-axis let's
be simple let's take the z-axis put the
spin in put the magnetic field along the
z-axis a spin in
particular the spin of a Charged
particle is a little electromagnet charg
particle spins around and as it spins
around there are currents that flow and
it creates a little
magnet put a magnet into a magnetic
field and you get an energy and
basically the energy is proportional to
the misalignment of the magnetic field
with the spin with the axis of the
spin and the simple
formula
uh is that the energy is proportional to
the dot product
of the spin with the magnetic
field that's where we're going to start
we're going to start with an energy
which is proportional of a magnetic
field and uh the magnetic field is along
the
z-axis so what is the dot product of the
spin with a magnetic field that's going
to be proportional to the Z component of
spin the dot product of the spin with
the magnetic field would be the
component of the spin along the uh along
the axis of the magnetic field that's a
guess okay take that as a guess which we
could then study and then ask if uh the
experiments on the spin agree with
it okay so we have a spin we have a
magnetic field along the z-axis let's
call it B
subz and we have a spin and the spin has
components Sigma X Sigma Y and sigma Z
people ask me incidentally why in the
book that I'm writing about quantum
mechanics there aren't more figures
there are lots of figures in the
classical mechanics book the reason is
is very simple I mean it's a real reason
you can't draw quantum mechanical
systems quantum mechanical systems are
by their very nature not things that you
can draw if you try to draw them you
will always be trying to draw things
which cannot simultaneously make sense
okay in particular if I try to draw the
components of the spin I'll be trying to
draw components of the spin which don't
commute with each other and and it
doesn't make sense to draw them
nevertheless there there it is magnetic
field in the
spin
and we're just going to right now we're
going to take this as a guess or as a
postulate the hamiltonian is just going
to be proportional to the component of
spin along the z-axis times something
proportional to the magnetic field I'm
not going to write out it contains the
electric charge it contains a magnetic
moment it contains a magnetic field but
let's just call the coefficient here
let's call it Omega over
two that's a definition of Omega if you
like whatever the right combination of
magnetic fields charge Magnetic Moment
particular charge Magnetic Moment and
magnetic field will lump them up and
call it Sigma over two sorry and call it
Omega over two and the reason for the
Omega will become clear shortly sorry
the reason for the two for both the
Omega and the two will become clear
shortly okay now what I want to
calculate what I want to calculate I
want to calculate the time derivative of
the averages of the all the components
of the
spin here we
have the Z component in the hamiltonian
but I want to find out how all the
components Sigma X Sigma Y and sigma Z
how they vary with time so in particular
I want to calculate the time derivative
dot for time derivative of Sigma X and
sigma Y and sigma Z well what is the
rule I'm afraid the rule has been erased
but I think you probably remember it the
time
and by definition now this means the
average of Sigma X I'm not going to
bother writing the the bracket
the uh angular brackets there
we now talking about the averages of
Sigma X Sigma Y and sigma Z and the time
derivatives of the
averages all right so if you remember
this is equal to minus
I times the
commutator of Sigma
x with the hamiltonian
right so the hamiltonian is Sigma
Z and we get another factor of Omega
over two oh uh yeah
that's
correct likewise
here Sigma y with Sigma
Z time Omega over
2 and likewise
here Sigma Z Sigma
Z now one of these is very easy which is
the easy one
the bottom one everything commutes with
itself right everything commutes with
itself so this is zero and what does it
tell us it tells us that the component
of the spin along the magnetic
field the average of it does not change
with time that also tells us well if it
was cl if we were doing classical
physics which we're not if we doing
classical physics it would tell us that
the angle of the little Vector here with
the magnetic field stays the same but
we're not we'll just take this for what
it says it says that the Z component
doesn't change with time the
average so that's the first thing we
discover now to go beyond this we have
to know what the commutation relations
are of the sigmas so let's work them out
I think we have enough time let's work
out the commutation relations of the
sigmas or pairs of them and uh see what
we get and then plug it into
here I'm going to start with Sigma X
Sigma Z but instead I'm going to do it
the opposite way I'm going to calculate
Sigma
Z Sigma X it's the same thing except
with a minus sign if when you
interchange the two of them so we'll
have to remember I'm calculating Sigma Z
Sigma X we have to remember to change a
sign okay so what is this this is the
product now everybody remember what
Sigma Z is as a matrix we're going to do
it now by
matrices say the way to calculate this
is to remember that Sigma Z and sigma X
are matrices or at least they have a
matrix
representation and we just have to
multiply the matrices Sigma Z what was
that that was one Zer one sorry one
minus
one and what about Sigma
X that's 0 1 1 0 that's the first term
in the commutator sigma Z * Sigma X and
then the other term is just to put them
in the opposite order
01 1
0 Time
1 0 -
one no we just take just the commutators
of the uh of the matrices is what it
comes down
to we could do it without the matrices
just by applying in The Operators to the
vectors to the vectors up and down and
we know what we know enough to actually
do that without actually using the
matrices but the matrices are a very
convenient tool for manipulating
operators operator product is the same
as matrix product okay so does everybody
know how to do a matrix product I hope
so let's do this one over
here the upper left hand corner is the
product of this this row with this
column 1 * 0 0 * 1
0 the upper right corner is the product
of this row with this column 1 * 1 0 0
1 the lower left corner is the product
of this row with this column that's
minus one and then the last one is this
row sorry this column times this row 0 *
1 and uh sorry no zero to this one this
one still
zero okay now let's do the other one
over here
minus 0 *
1 this one time this one zero this one *
this one minus one this one this one
time this one 1
Zer
uh I think I missed the sign
somewhere yeah no no it's right it's
right this is
plus
minus okay so this we got they just gave
the same
thing but with a minus sign sorry this
minus this
gave two terms which add so the
commutator is just equal to the
commutator itself is just equal to
01 no is equal to
twice minus one
0 now do you recognize this thing over
here if I put an i over here and an i
over here you might recognize it as
being related to Sigma y let me write
down Sigma y Sigma Y is equal to - i i0
0 and what happens if I multiply Sigma I
by
I I * minus I is
1 and I * I is min -1 so what this is is
it's just twice I Sigma y
2 I Sigma y that's kind of neat it's
closing up on itself commutators of
sigmas with sigmas are sigmas that's
good because it's going to allow me to
write equations for the time derivatives
of sigmas which are just going to be
sigmas
again okay so let's uh let's see what we
have we have commutator Sigma Z with
Sigma
X is equal to twice I Sigma y
Y and now I'll write down the rest of
them incidentally as I said if you want
to get the opposite order you just
change the sign Sigma Z Sigma x with
Sigma
Y is equal to 2 I Sigma
Z and zxy sigma y XY Z Sigma Z is equal
to 2 I Sigma X
these are the three commutation did
these did this remind you of
anything do you remember the Pome
brackets of angular
momentum the Pome brackets of angular
momentum were LZ LX equal l y l y LX l y
is equal to LZ and l y LZ is equal to LX
so apart from a factor of 2 I remember
there is an i in the connection between
Pome brackets and uh
and um and
commutators these are essentially apart
from a factor of two which we can absorb
they're essentially angular momentum uh
Pome
brackets that's there's an important
clue there for the meaning of angular
momentum uh but uh we're not going to
dwell on it for the moment this these
are the commutation relations of the
components of the spin
and they just give back comp the
components of the spin again with this
funny ordering zxy XY Z yzx they're just
permuted
cyclically okay so let's go over to here
now this now
becomes Min -
I Omega / 2 and now what's the
commutator of Sigma x with Sigma
Z it's - 2 I Sigma
y so we get another - 2
I Sigma
y the twos cancel that was the reason
that I put a two in the denominator here
in the first place because I knew it was
going to cancel so let's cancel the
two and we have Min - I * - I which is
minus1 so what we get is minus Omega
Sigma
y notice that the I went
away the I went away we I was worried
about it about half an hour ago that oh
my goodness time derivatives of real
things are going to get imaginary but
they didn't they didn't because the
commutators themselves had imaginary
coefficients and that's General that's
General okay so there we are we have
have Sigma x
dot is equal to minus Omega Sigma
Y and sigma y
dot here we have the relationship for
Sigma Y and it involves twice Sigma X
the correct relationship if we work it
out is that this is equal to
plus plus Omega Sigma X
okay so Sigma Z dot is zero but what's
happening to Sigma X and sigma y can you
see what's happening to Sigma X and
sigma
y you recognize this these
equations these are the
equations for a thing moving in circular
motion
right what's happening is simple the
exp in the sense of expectation values
expectation values are real
numbers and uh in the sense of
expectation values the spin Vector is
processing
around the z-axis it's processing around
the z-axis sigma x dot is minus Omega
Sigma y Sigma y dot is plus Omega Sigma
X this is the same kind of formula that
we discovered in classical mechanics
when we talked about a rotor you
remember the rotor and we also put the
rotor in a magnetic field the angular
momentum executed exactly the same and
it's also the gyroscope procession it's
basically gyroscopic
procession a spin a quantum mechanical
spin in the sense of expectation
values it doesn't make any sense to say
that the quantum mechanical operators
themselves uh process that doesn't mean
anything quantum mechanical operators
are just these matrices they don't do
anything but because the state vectors
change with time the expectation values
the average values of the spin execute a
motion which is basically the same as a
classical
rotor processing in a magnetic field
okay so we have
now solve the problem of a spin in a
magnetic field we've solved the hardest
possible problem associated with a
single
spin uh there is no hamiltonian which is
more complicated than this for the
single spin it's the most General you of
course you could put the SP you could
put the magnetic field in the X
Direction all right there's a little yes
you can solve a harder
problem uh you could put the uh the um
spin along some uh peculiar axis but
what you would find after you work the
whole thing out is that it would just
process around the peculiar axis of the
magnetic field same thing you just
rotate it uh so that so that the
magnetic field is pointing in a
different direction excuse me any hints
on what's that any hints on why that's
the correct value for the hamoni there
really aren't very many operators okay
so
let's here's a general you can work this
out yourself this is not hard to
prove the most
General hermiss operator in two
Dimensions is a linear combination of
the unit
operator Sigma X Sigma Y and sigma Z the
most General Herm Mission operator is a
linear combination of these putting a
unit operator into a hamiltonian that's
like adding a constant to the energy
unit operators commute with
everything so putting a unit operator in
is not inter interesting it does nothing
so we get rid of this the next
possibility is a general combination
linear combination add them up of a
coefficient time Sigma X another
coefficient time Sigma Y and another
coefficient time Sigma
Z that just corresponds to putting the
magnetic field at some uh at some
angle it's just
uh the simple case where we only took
one of
these is the magnetic field
along the z-axis if we took a general
linear combination let's say n subx
Sigma X Plus n suby Sigma y plus n subz
Sigma Z this would just correspond to
the component of the spin along the N
axis and you would do exactly the same
calculation except you might work
instead in the
basis of igen vectors of Sig in so it
really is the most General hamiltonian
that you can uh that you can write down
and that's just because a
two-dimensional space is so simple there
just aren't very many independent
operators in
it uh it just is nothing
else can you comment on the relation
between the the two dimensional spaces
is the space of
States think Dimensions recession right
but we worked yeah but remember for
every direction that you can think of
there is a state for which that
component of the spin is definite but
that's secondary here we're not uh that
we that didn't play much very much of a
role here we just follow the
rules and uh but yes I mean there there
are two things going on here and this is
a good place to to focus on those two
things there are three vectors the
vectors in real space those are the
components of the averages of Sigma and
there's the two-dimensional space of
states and they're quite different
things although they are
related
yeah does Omega represent some proper
the magnetic
field
it's Omega is basically the product of
the magnetic field times the Magnetic
Moment of the little spin right
I there may be a two I have to remember
but uh no I don't think there uh yeah
there is a two yeah Omega over two is
the product of the Magnetic Moment with
a uh with a magnetic
field our original technique for
creating Sigma Z was to put it in a
magnetic field and have a photon below
that was last that was last
year right you're right
um right so I mean if we pursued this
and coupled it to a a field we would
would see that thing yeah right if we
couple the spin now forget the
procession if we couple the spin to the
magnetic field then there will be two
energy states for example if the
magnetic field is along the
z-axis then the energy of the UP State
and the down state will be different
they'll differ by amount Omega up will
have energy Omega over 2 down we'll have
energy minus Omega over 2 and there will
be an energy difference of
Omega all right so one of them has
higher energy one of them has lower
energy what happens to a real spin if
you wait long
enough if you put it in a magnetic field
the answer is eventually the higher
energy state will emit a photon and what
will be the fre what will be the energy
of the photon Omega just the difference
between the upper energy and the lower
energy
and in the process of emitting the
photon it will
flip so these things are all certainly
connected but
uh all right we've solved a real genuine
quantum mechanics problem yeah so why is
V not treated as an operator what's that
why is the magnetic field not treated as
an Valu
is if you were to think of the mag the
magnet as part of the quantum mechanic
mechical system whenever you whenever
you're facing the problem of a real
Quantum
system which is being in interaction
with a heavy system with a system like a
heavy Magnet or some other kind of
detector an almost classical
system uh you don't bother trying to
think of the heavy system Quantum
mechanically you just say it has some
now that has to be justified this is not
OB is to
justify uh why don't we have to think of
the magnet as part of the quantum
mechanical system that's another way of
asking the same
question and the answer is that it's so
big and it's so heavy that it doesn't
fluctuate much but event and eventually
we want to address that problem for the
moment we just think of the magnet as
part of a heavy apparatus which is sort
of fixed and it's there and nothing that
that electron can do is going to cause
that the magnetic field to change it's
just stuck there for and uh and we get
to think of it
deterministically when do we get to
think about a thing deterministically we
get to think about a thing
deterministically when it's so heavy and
so many degrees of freedom that when we
calculate the quantum mechanics of it we
find that the fluctuations are really
small but that has not been established
yet so far we've divided the world into
the Quant
and the apparatuses the heavy
apparatuses which we don't have to deal
with Quant mechanically that of course
has to be a temporary thing real
apparatuses are made out of the same
thing as the systems we study and so at
some point we have to come back and say
what was the what was the
justification for saying the
apparatus was allowed to be considered
just classically you just point it in
some direction and that's the way it is
and the spin dealt with Quantum
mechanically we have to come back and
answer that but uh you know my usual
uh statement at this point is not
tonight Sig X Sig X do and Sig y dot
those
arees yes yes that's what you do the
experiment what
what yeah
no in an unpredictable
manner M right yes the answer is yes it
will occasionally
fail but that has little to do with
quantum mechanics well it has to do with
quantum mechanics but it has to do with
the use of statistics and probability
why does probability work we make a
basic postulate and that's that if you
do an experiment over enough times
the average value that you get in the
laboratory will agree to within small
Precision with the mathematical averages
that you calculate from a probability
distribution I am not going to try to
justify that the reason is I don't know
why it's
true and uh why does probability
work why if I tell you you flip a coin a
thousand
times does it come up heads uh 500 times
no there's no such
prediction certainly I mean it might
come up 500 times heads but there's no
prediction that says it
does will it come up 500 times plus or
minus square root of a th000 plus orus
30 that's the margin of
error not every time no so there's no
such
prediction what can you say you can say
it will probably come up
uh you know put we get into the cycle
how about if I do it a million times
will it certainly come
up 500,000 plus a minus square root of n
no no matter how many times you do it
there is no hard and fast prediction
from probability that any particular
thing will
happen why does it work Jesus it beats
me but it
does many you know I'm not the only one
who've been puzzled by this I mean you
know I used to like the joke that this
is probably the reason that the Einstein
didn't like quantum
mechanics say it again
on
compon
yeah original
now we could have done the same
calculation by instead of putting Sigma
Z here putting
this sigma.
n sigma. n is the
Matrix in the notation that we've been
using up till now where the sigma
matrices are the things I wrote down it
would be the
Matrix
uh N is a unit
Vector n subz minus n subz
nx- i n y and NX plus i n
y it's just taking the components of N
and multiplying them with a
corresponding components of Sigma and
then you could start with this and say
this is the H I'll put an Omega over two
and take this to be the
hamiltonian and then recalculate what
happens to the different components of
spin well the component of spin along
the N axis what would we do then then we
would have to
calculate commutators of the various
components of the spin with sigma. n
sigma.
in what about the component along the N
axis what happen to
it commutate is zero right sigma. n
commutes with sigma. n so we would find
out that the component of the spin along
the N axis would be the thing that
doesn't
change how about the components the spin
perpendicular to that axis we could work
that
out and we would discover that the spin
processes about the N
axis that's a good exercise to try to do
I mean was asking what would the refle
the
orientation if you if you want say it
again I was asking whether the Omega the
value of Omega reflected the orientation
of the St and you moved it from the
Omega the no the Omega is just a
number because you put the
in if you
by orientation you mean plus or minus
one or you mean
Direction no no no no no no no no no no
no Omega doesn't have to do with the
direction Omega is just the magnitude of
the magnetic field magnitude of the
magnetic field times the magnitude of
the Magnetic
Moment no not dotted they're just
numbers they're numbers the dot product
is between Sigma and n
Omega is just a spectator it's just a
number it's just a
number oh you can if you like you you
could take this Omega and put it with
the end if you wanted
to what you think
theega depends orientation of what
depends on the orientation of the spin
one of us is confused I'm not sure which
confusion is that the when you had Sig Z
up there that implies the magnetic field
in the Z Direction here the magnetic
field was in the Z Direction and that's
the Omega Z you had right Omega Z where
did I have omega z
h sorry Sigma Z Sigma Z yes Sigma Z
where is the where is the the
um the spatial Vector of the spin
represent Omega in means means do
product I can't remember which book I
read it in but they said whenever you're
talking spin you're really not talking
one half you're
talking that is that yeah I think I read
that I read that too I think it was in N
gingrich's last book
I don't know look sigma. n stands for
Sigma X and X Plus Sigma Y and Y plus
Sigma Z and Z exactly as if Sigma was a
classical
Vector but of course it's not it's just
a collection of three matrices so this
stands for Matrix this stands for a
single Matrix which happens to be the
sum of three particular matrices but
that's the definition of sigma. n if you
like these are the components of N and
they determine the direction of the
magnetic field we multiply that by Omega
over 2 which is just a number just a
number nothing uh nothing more
complicated than a
number and this is what Sigma DN means
if the magnetic field is along the
z-axis then the only component of n
which is not non zero would be n
subz okay if the magnetic field was
along the
z-axis then we would
say only n
subz if you like would you like me to
write down the relationship between n
and the magnetic field the relationship
between n and the magnetic field is that
the magnetic field
Vector is equal to the magnitude of the
magnetic field time the unit Vector
n okay the magnetic field as a vector is
the magnitude of the magnetic field
times the vector n and that stands for a
magnetic field that's pointing along the
N axis with magnitude
B once we know
that then we can basically identify the
magnetic field with n apart from a
numerical coefficient numerical
coefficient is buried in Omega
here once we know that we can write this
as the spin dotted into B so I'm not
sure what the questions are there's some
there's something which is bothering
some of you I'm not sure what it
is when you you get a frequency is that
frequency always the same or does it
depend on
the it depends on the magnitude of the
magnetic field nothing
more you're talking about the fre quency
of the photon yeah now the frequency of
the photon is always just the difference
of the energy of the upper energy level
and the lower energy level and it is
always just
Omega doesn't depend on the
right if you take sigma. n and you ask
what its igen values are the igen values
don't depend on N they're plus and minus
one in any direction
h no just the the uh the igen values
here let's write out sigma. n all right
here's an exercise for you it should be
done sigma. n is n subz * Sigma subz
that's NZ minus
NZ plus
NX time Sigma X that's that
minus or NY Sigma
y That's n.
Sigma question what are the igen values
of this Matrix somebody's worked them
out I know that somebody in this room
has worked them out where uh who was it
uh
H the igen values of this Matrix here
for any NS as long as they're unit
vectors if n is the components of a unit
vector
in other words N x^2 + n y^2 + n z^2 is
equal to 1 you will find that the igen
values of this Matrix are always plus or
minus
one the this this is simply the
statement that M no matter what
direction you point your detected your
apparatus when the apparatus acts it
gives you plus or minus one okay so
whatever Direction you take here
the igen values of this Matrix are plus
or minus
one if you know a little bit about
matrices for those who know a little bit
about matrices let's prove
it the trace of a matrix is the sum of
its igen
values the trace means the sum of the
diagonal
elements all right first step there are
two igen values let's call them Lambda 1
and Lambda 2 and the trace of the Matrix
is zero this one plus this one and that
tells us that Lambda 1 + Lambda 2 is 0
or Lambda 1 is equal to minus Lambda 2
so there are two igen values and they're
equal and
opposite what about the determinant of
the
matrix it's the product of the igen
values so we now know they come in equal
and opposite pairs what's the product
what's the uh determinant the
determinant of this
Matrix is equal to
minus n z^ 2 this times
this minus this time this and that's -
nx^ 2 - n y^ 2
right NX plus i n y * NX - n y is nx2 +
n y^2 here it is and what is nx2 + n Y2
+ and z^2 one so the determinant which
is the product of the igen
values is equal to
minus1 there's only one solution Lambda
1 + Lambda
2 is equal to zero that says Lambda 1 is
equal to minus Lambda 2 and the product
is equal to minus1 there's only one such
pair it's plus one and minus one so all
such matrices of this form have igen
values which are plus or minus one and
therefore the energy levels are always
plus or minus Omega over
2 one of them plus Omega over 2 the
other minus Omega over 2 and when you
flip from one to another you get Omega
worth of
energy right so it doesn't matter which
way things are pointing in yeah I I
think it's time to go but if an electron
is let's say in the
Z yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah that's right
in in studying in yes I should have said
in studying the procession here we've
ignored the possibility that it can
radiate a
photon now the probability to radiate a
photon per unit
time uh can be pretty
small can be very very small small in
particular if the energy differences are
very small as they would be in an
ordinary magnetic field it will process
many many times before it emits a photon
so my question is if it
does emit a photon since it's not
exactly flipping it's only going
90° going from up to down
okay remember the two
I the two igen vectors up and down or
left and right or in and
out correspond to opposite orientations
of the uh of the spin even though the
state vectors are orthogonal the
directions in space are 180 degrees
apart so here imaginary
situation is not suddenly do something
other what it was doing or oral to what
it was doing
there's a probability for the electron
to Decay and emit a
photon it is and that probability per
unit time is typically small so you
could be unlucky and after a quarter of
a revolution it might emit its
Photon but that's extremely
unlikely you can estimate how many is it
am I asking answering your question I'm
not sure no really is really either in
the direction it was going or flip
opposite it won't suddenly go to some
other weird angle like X to y z I think
the question is since it's not feels
like the electron
you no it's in a super position of being
up and down it's one of the two of those
it's only the a average which is sort of
in a campus
Direction it's in a superposition of
being up and
down if it's down and down is the lower
energy state it won't radiate if it's up
it will radiate so if you put the
electron in some other direction there
will be some probability for it to
radiate and a probability for it not to
radiate the probability for it to
radiate is the probability that it was
up yeah
very
confusing very
confusing
right okay now I see what was bothering
you if the magnetic field is that way
and the spin is aligned that way you
might have thought that when it jumps
you only emit half the energy of a
photon of the pH half the energy
no what's correct is that the
probability for it to emit a photon is2
why because there's half a probability
that this is actually down and half a
probability that it's up if you were to
measure the upness and down of it so
that means the average energy that it
emits is
half but it either emits Omega or it
doesn't emit at all good for more please
visit us at stanford.edu